The President: Station this is your President.
Do you hear me?
NASA: Station, this is Houston are you ready for the event?
Station: Yes, we're ready for the event.
NASA: White House, this is
Mission Control, Houston.
Please call Station
for a voice check.
The President:
Do you hear me?
Cmdr. Whitson: Yes, sir.
We have you
loud and clear.
The President: Well,
that's what we like --
great American
equipment that works.
And this isn't easy.
(Laughter.)
I want to say it's very exciting to be here today
-- very, very
exciting -- and to speak
to you live with three
brave American astronauts.
These are our finest.
These are great, great
Americans, great people.
Two join us from orbit
aboard the
International Space Station: Commander Peggy Whitson and
Colonel Jack Fischer.
And Peggy Whitson has been
setting records, and we're
going to talk about
that very soon.
I'm here in the Oval
Office, along with my
daughter Ivanka and
astronaut Kate Rubins, who
recently returned from space and from the Space Station.
Together, we are being
joined by students all
across America, thousands
and thousands of students
who are learning --
they're learning about
space, learning about a
lot of other things -- and
they're watching this conversation from the classroom.
And, all over, we have
astronauts and we have
everybody, who are flying
right now,
17,000 miles per hour.
That's about as fast
as I've ever heard.
I wouldn't want to be
flying 17,000 miles an hour.
But that's what you do.
Peggy, Jack, and Kate,
I know that America's
students are thrilled
to hear from you.
But first, I want to
say that this is a very
special day in the
glorious history of
American spaceflight.
Today, Commander Whitson,
you have broken the record
for the most total time
spent in space by an
American astronaut --
534 days and counting.
That's an incredible
record to break.
And on behalf of our
nation and, frankly, on
behalf of the world, I'd
like to congratulate you.
That is really something.
And I'd like to know,
how does it feel to have
broken such a big and
important record?
Cmdr. Whitson: Well, it's
actually a huge honor to
break a record like this,
but it's an honor for me
basically to be
representing all the folks
at NASA who make this
spaceflight possible and
who make me setting
this record feasible.
And so it's a very
exciting time to be at NASA.
We are all very much
looking forward, as
directed by your new NASA
bill -- we're excited
about the missions
to Mars in the 2030s.
And so we actually,
physically, have hardware
on the ground that's being
built for the SLS rocket
that's going to
take us there.
And, of course, the
hardware being built now
is going to be for the
test flights that will
eventually get us there.
But it's a very exciting
time, and I'm so
proud of the team.
The President: Great.
And what are we learning
from having you spending
your time up there?
I know so much research
is done; I'm getting a
glimpse of some of it
right here in the Oval Office.
What are we learning
by being in space?
Cmdr. Whitson: Well, I think
probably the International
Space Station is providing
a key bridge from us
living on Earth to going
somewhere into deep space.
So on those Mars missions,
we need to better
understand how
microgravity is really
affecting our body, and we
need to understand
it in great detail.
So, many of the studies
are looking at the human body.
We're also looking at
things that involve
operations of a space
vehicles on these
long-duration missions
and the technological
advancements that
will be required.
For instance, on a
multiyear Mars mission,
we're going to need to be
able to close the life
support system, and that
means we, right now, for
instance, are taking solar
power that we collect, and
using it to break apart
water into oxygen and hydrogen.
The oxygen, we
breathe, of course.
We use the hydrogen,
combine it back with the
CO2 that we take out of
the air, and make more water.
But water is such a
precious resource up here
that we also are cleaning
up our urine and
making it drinkable.
And it's really not
as bad as it sounds.
The President:
Well, that's good.
I'm glad to hear that.
(Laughter.)
Better you than me.
I will say, Colonel
Fischer, you just arrived,
and how was your trip?
Complicated?
Easy?
How did it go?
Col. Fischer: Oh, sir,
it was awesome.
It made even my beloved
F-22 feel a little
bit underpowered.
I launched in a Russian
vehicle with my Russian
friend, Fyodor Yurchikhin,
from Kazakhstan.
Got the immediate
perspective change as we
got to orbit, and I saw
that frail, thin blue line
of life around the Earth.
Six hours later, we're
docked at the station.
The next day, I install an
experiment in the Japanese
module that's going to be
looking at new drugs and
how we can make those
drugs for muscular
dystrophy, Alzheimer's,
multi-drug-resistant
bacteria -- all
sorts of things.
A couple hours later, I
watched our crewmate,
Thomas Pesquet, a
Frenchman, drive a
Canadian robotic arm to
capture a spaceship from
Virginia, carrying 3.5
tons of cargo and science
that's going to keep us
busy for the next few
months, and dock
that to the station.
Sir, it's amazing.
Oh, and then, you know,
now I'm talking to the
President of the United States while hanging from a wall.
It's amazing.
The International Space
Station is, by far, the
best example of
international cooperation
and what we can do when
we work together in the
history of humanity.
And I am so proud
to be a part of it.
And it's just cool.
(Laughter.)
Like, yesterday, I had -- well,
there you go -- there's
our resident space ninja
doing the gravity
demonstration.
And yesterday morning, I
had my coffee in floaty
ball form, and, sir,
it was delicious.
So, it's awesome.
The President: Tell me,
Mars -- what do you see a
timing for actually
sending humans to Mars?
Is there a schedule?
And when would you
see that happening?
Cmdr. Whitson: Well, I think as
your bill directed, it
will be approximately
in the 2030s.
As I mentioned, we
actually are building
hardware to test the new
heavy launch vehicle, and
this vehicle will take us
further than we've ever
been away from
this planet.
Unfortunately, spaceflight
takes a lot of time and
money, so getting there
will require some
international cooperation
to get it to be a
planet-wide approach
in order to make it
successful, just because
it is a very
expensive endeavor.
But it so
worthwhile doing.
The President: Well, we
want to try and do it
during my first term or,
at worst, during my second term.
So we'll have to speed
that up a little bit, okay?
Cmdr. Whitson: (Laughter.)
We'll do our best.
The President:
Oh, you will.
And I have great
respect for you folks.
It's amazing what you do.
And I just want to
introduce another great one.
Kate Rubins is with us
today, and she has been so
impressive with research
and so many other things
having to do with NASA.
And, Kate, I understand
you're the first person to
sequence DNA in space.
Can you tell
us about that?
Dr. Rubins: Yeah.
So that was actually just
this last summer, and it's
a real example of what we
can do with technology
and innovation.
We've got a sequencer
down to the size of your
cellphone, and we were
actually able to fly that
onboard the space station
and sequence DNA.
It's not just the
technology demonstration,
but we can actually use
that to do things like
detect microbes on the
space station, look
at astronaut health.
We can easily use that in
Earth-based settings, too,
to look for disease
outbreaks and to do rural
healthcare as well.
The President:
That's fantastic.
That is really great.
I saw some of the work,
and it's incredible.
You know, I've been
dealing with politicians
so much, I'm so much more
impressed with these people.
You have no idea.
Now, speaking of another
impressive person --
Ivanka, you've been very
much interested in this program.
Tell us something
about it.
Ms. Trump: Hi,
Dr. Whitson.
First of all,
congratulations on your
incredible
milestone today.
You may know that my
father recently signed the
Inspire Women Act
to encourage female
participation in STEM
fields across all
aerospace areas, and
really with a focus on NASA.
So encouraging women and
girls to pursue STEM
careers is a major priority for this administration.
And today we are sitting
with an amazing example of
that -- Dr. Rubins,
and you, Dr. Whitson.
So I would love to hear
from you, what was the
impetus for you to get
involved in the sciences?
Dr. Rubins: Yeah, so
when I around fifteen, I
actually went to a
conference, and that was
very inspiring for me.
It was sort of the
beginning of recombinant
DNA and understanding
biology.
And so just that exposure
to scientists and the
kinds of things that you
can do with science and
technology innovation.
Ms. Trump: Amazing.
Dr. Whitson?
Cmdr. Whitson: For me, it was
actually the Apollo
program was my
inspiration, and that was
when it became a dream
to become an astronaut.
But I don't really think
it became a goal until I
graduated from high
school, when the first
female astronauts
were selected.
And seeing those role
models, and with the
encouragement of my
parents and various
mentors in college and
graduate school, and when
I started working at
Rice, that's what made it
possible, I think, to
become an astronaut.
And it took me a lot
longer to become an
astronaut than I ever
really wanted it to take,
but I do think I'm better
at my job because
of the journey.
Ms. Trump: You're an incredible inspiration to us all.
So I would also like to
ask you one more question.
I'm incredibly curious, as
I'm sure all the students
across the country are,
to know what a day in the
life in space is like.
Could you share what a
typical day looks like,
what the challenges are,
just any special moments?
Cmdr. Whitson: Well, a typical
day, we wake up and look
at the messages from the
ground, because we have a
huge ground team that's
working overnight to
prepare changes or the
details of the tests that
we're going to be
performing over the
course of the day.
So first thing I do is
check out that,
see what's changed.
But on any given day, it can be so dramatically different.
On one day, we might be
focusing on science.
On another day, we might
be repairing the carbon
dioxide removal system.
On another day, soon Jack
and I are going
to do a spacewalk.
We talked about, last
Saturday, we did
robotics operations.
I love the diversity of
the different
activities that we do.
Plus, you know, we have
over 200 investigations
ongoing onboard the space
station, and I just think
that's a phenomenal
part of the day.
Of course, there's also
just the living and,
onboard the space station,
it's such a unique and
novel environment.
Nothing that we're
used to on the ground.
And it's so special to
just be in zero gravity.
So Jack is the new guy
here, and I think he can
probably give you a better perspective on what that's like.
Col. Fischer: Well, you know,
everything here -- my dad
always said that if you
love what you do, you
never work a day
in your life.
And we work really hard up
here, but it's not really
work, it's just fun.
It's like playing fort
almost, only you're
changing the world
while you do it.
And then on the off time,
the other morning I was
working out, and on our
machine that we work out
on, right below it
is the Cupola window.
And so when you're on
the device where you do
crunches, every time you
come up,
you see out the window.
And it's awesome because
you kind of go, crunch,
"Oh, my gosh,
that's beautiful!
I got to do that again."
Crunch, "Oh my gosh,
that's beautiful."
It's awesome.
Everything we do here is
fun, and it feels so great
to know that we're making
a difference on the ground
and for the future
of humanity as well.
So it's an incredible,
incredible job.
The President: You're
making a great difference,
I have to say.
And this is a very
exciting time for our
country, and you see
what's happening with our
country in terms of jobs,
in terms of business, and
there's such excitement
and such enthusiasm.
Many American
entrepreneurs are
racing into space.
I have many friends that
are so excited about space.
They want to get involved
in space from the
standpoint of
entrepreneurship and business.
Tell us about the
opportunities that could
exist for the next
generation of scientists
and engineers.
Is that something that you
think a student -- because
you have so many students,
hundreds of thousands
watching -- is that
something that you think
that students should be
focusing, or should they
be thinking about
other subjects?
What do you think are the
opportunities for young
students wanting to
be involved in space?
Col. Fischer: Sir, absolutely.
I think that this is
probably the most exciting
in space exploration,
certainly in my lifetime.
We are about to just have
an explosion of activity.
There is so much
involvement on the space
station with commercial
industries and
commercial partners.
We have an entire program
to manage the science.
NASA has done a wonderful
job of seeding a new
industry with the
Commercial Crew Program
and the Commercial Cargo
Program so that we can
build the infrastructure
we need for the
future exploration.
One thing I love about
American entrepreneurs is,
once you get them going,
you better stand out of
their way because they're
going to start chucking.
And we're about
to that point.
NASA is taking on that
expensive, hard, complex
task of going further and
deeper into space with the
wonderful new rocket,
Space Launch System and Orion.
And then, as soon as we
break open that door, this
incredible infrastructure
that we've been building
is going to be right there
to pick up the baton and
continue into the stars.
I would say to all
the students that are
watching, the time to
get excited is now.
If you aren't studying
science and math, you
might want to think about
that because our future in
the stars starts now, and
you can be a part of that
if, like Dr. Whitson, you
can find that passion and
work really hard.
And we're going to find a
permanent foothold in the
stars for humanity
if you do that.
The President:
Well, thank you.
So well said.
And I have to say, there's
tremendous military
application in space.
We're rebuilding our
military like never before.
We're ordering equipment,
and we're going to have
the strongest military
that we've ever had, the
strongest military that
the world has ever seen,
and there's been no time
where we need it more.
And I'm sure that every
student watching wants to
know, what is next for
Americans in space.
I'm very proud that I just
signed a bill committing
NASA to the aim of sending
America astronauts to Mars.
So we'll do that.
I think we'll do it a lot
sooner than we're even thinking.
So which one of you is
ready to go to Mars?
Are you ready?
And I think you're ready.
I know you're
ready, right?
We just discussed that.
She'd like to go to
Mars very quickly.
Who's ready to go
to Mars up there?
Cmdr. Whitson: We are absolutely
ready to go to Mars.
It's going to be a
fantastic journey getting
there, and very exciting
times, and all of us
would be happy to go.
But I want all the young
people out there to
recognize that the real
steps are going to be
taken in a few years.
And so by studying math,
science, engineering, any
kind of technology, you're
going to have a part in
that, and that will
be very exciting.
The President: I just want
to thank you very much.
And, Dr. Whitson, I just
-- congratulations.
Amazing.
What an amazing thing
that you've done.
Everybody here -- I know
you're family -- but
everybody here is
incredibly proud of the
record you just broke.
I hope that every young
American watching today
finds, in your example, a
reason to love space and
think about space because
many great things are
going to come out,
tremendous discoveries in
medicine and so
many other fields.
So thank you very much.
I want to say God bless
you, God bless America.
We are very, very proud
of you, and very proud
of your bravery.
Thank you very much.